Inventory of the James Barron Papers (1) 1776-1899
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Box 1, 1776-1808, 1851, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1-82)
  - Items concerning the skirmish between the U.S.S. Chesapeake and the English warship Leopard and the Court of Enquiry that follow this event, 23 June 1807., 37 items. (Box-folder 1:50-82)
    - Journal Copy - Copy of a portion of the "Journal," or Log Book of the U.S. Ship Chesapeake, [June] 1807., 3 pages. AD. (Box-folder 1:58)
      Item was sent to Robert Smith, Secretary of the Navy, [by James Barron], by way of Capt. Gordon.
    - Letter - R[ober]t Smith, Navy Department, to Capt. James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 12 September 1807., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:59)
      Enclosing a call for a Court of Enquiry to investigate conduct of James Barron, for October 5.
    - Warrant - "Warrant for the Court and notice to J.B. to attend as his conduct is to be inquired into," issued by Capt. Alexander Murry for meeting on "October 5 next." [ ] 1807., 2 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 1:60)
    - Letter Copy - Copy of a letter from Thomas Jefferson, Washington, to Gov. William H. Cabell, 29 June 1807., 1 page. TCop. (Box-folder 1:61)
      Re: the chance that the Chesapeake affair might be cause for a declaration of war.
    - Receipt - of Stephen Decatur, Jr., for papers received from Commodore James Barron, 1 July 1807., 2 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 1:62)
    - Letter - [James Barron], Back River, near Hampton, to Dr. Bolter, 3 July 1807., 5 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 1:63)
      Re: his wound, which makes it impossible for him to sit up; and his comments on the affair of the Chesapeake and the Leopard.
    - Letter - James Barron, near Hampton, to Capt. C. Gordon, July 1807., 2 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 1:64)
      Re: the action of the Chesapeake on 22 of June.
    - Letter - J.E. Douglas, Ship Bellona, Hampton Roads, to [James Barron], 10 July 1807., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:65)
      A list of the armament and complement of officers and men on the Ship Leopard; and a copy of the order of 1 June 1807 given by G. Berkeley, given in Halifax, Nova Scotia, under which the attack was made by the Leopard.
    - Statement - regarding the General Order of Admiral Berkeley, [by James Barron], [ ] 1807., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 1:65)
    - Letter - L.W. Tazewell, Judge Advocate, U.S. Ship Chesapeake, to Commodore James Barron, Hampton, 8 October 1807., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:66)
      Re: postponement of the trial to Friday the 16th, due to Barron's "feeble state of health."
    - Letter - James Barron, near Hampton, to Robert B. Taylor, 4 December 1807., 2 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 1:67)
      Re: the taking of Mr. Saunders to assist Taylor in the defense of James Barron.
    - Letter - Henry Hiort, Capitol Hill, City of Washington, to [James Barron], 13 December 1807., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:68)
      Re: the day fixed for the Court Martial.
    - Letter - P. McLachlin, Charleston, to Commodore James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 2 January 1808., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:69)
      Re: the Report of the Court of Enquiry... "Rascally.. .grounded with prejudice.
    - Charges - against Capt. James Barron at the General Court Martial at Norfolk, Virginia, 4 January 1808., 6 pages. AD. (Box-folder 1:70)
    - Testimony - at the trial in The "Chesapeake-Leopard Affair," involving James Barron's Court Martial, January 1808., pages. ADr. (Box-folder 1:71)
      Testimony of Captain Gordon in "Chesapeake-Leopard" trial. ADr; Testimony of Captain Hall in "Chesapeake-Leopard" trial. 8 pages. ADr; Capt. Gordon's 2nd dep'n. 4 pages. ADr; "Testimony" at the Chesapeake- Leopard trial. ADr. (See printed report of the Court Martial Proceedings, Box 13.)
    - Abstract - "An abstract taken from the Log Book of the U.S. Frigate Chesapeake, for Captn. Gordon.", [1808]., 3 pages. (Box-folder 1:72)
    - Testimony - [by James Barron] at the Court Martial, [1808]., 4 pages. (Box-folder 1:73a)
    - Amendments - to report the Chesapeake Court Martial [made by James Barron], [1808]., 3 pages. (Box-folder 1:73b)
    - Letter - B. Cocke, Washington, to Captain James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 13 January 1808., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:74)
      Re: rumors of war with England; suggesting that subscriptions be raised for a ship of commerce to be commanded by James Barron, and that the President might remit his sentence.
    - Letter - James Madison, Dept. of State, Washington, D.C., to [Littleton] W[aller] Tazewell, 18 January 1808., 1 page. LS. (Box-folder 1:74a)
      Re: Madison's appearance as a witness to the trial of Commodore James Barron.
    - Autograph report - of "the General Court Martial assembled on Board the United States Ship Chesapeake...to try James Barron, Esq., a Captain in the Navy.", 8 February 1808., 22 pages. AD,E. (Box-folder 1:75)
      The charges and decisions are given in detail; part of page 22, the last paragraph has been cut away. Endorsement [by James Barron]: "The Congress of the U. States took up this affair and appointed a Committee to examine into my conduct. That Committee acquited (sic) me of all sort of blame; their report is to be found on their records."
    - Letter - Anonymous letter from Washington to Capt. James Barron, Hampton, 5 March 1808., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:76)
      States that "Doct. Bullus has been your decided enemy."
    - Letter - B. Cocke, Washington, to Capt. James Barron, Hampton, 7 March 1808., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:77)
      Re: the decision of the Court Martial, which has not yet appeared.
    - Letter - Jesse D. Elliot, U.S. Frigate Chesapeake, to Como. James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 12 May 1808., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:78)
      Re: Charges against Fitz. H. Babbit.
    - Letter - B. Cocke, Washington, to Captain James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 13 June 1808., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:79)
      Re: the chance of the President's remitting the sentence of the Court Martial of James Barron, the President is expected hourly from Monticello.
    - Letter - Ro[bert] Saunders, Williamsburg, to Commodore James Barron, Hampton, 30 June 1808., 2 letters. Original-6 pages. Copy-8 pages. ALS. Copy included. (Box-folder 1:80)
      Re: dissatisfaction with the outcome of the Court Martial of James Barron, criticism of the trial and "this unhallowed sentence against you"; and hopes for a full publication of the trial.
      Copy of the above included.
    - Comment on the trial of Comm. B[arron] in connection with the Chesapeake affair, n.d., 4 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 1:81)
    - Comment on improper swearing of witnesses at the Court Martial of Capt. James Barron, n.d., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 1:81)
    - Newspaper clipping - of report of The Chesapeake-Leopard Affair as given by the late Adm. Davenport, Commander of the Leopard, [1851]., NCL. (Box-folder 1:82)
  Series 2: Box 2
- Box 2, 1810-1815. (Box-folder 2:1-46)
  At the beginning of this box is to be found a curious ten page document from John Peake to Lord Gambier, 4 June 1811; in it he recommends "an entirely new system for naval vessels." Also from this period, 7 September 1811 is the letter from W. Lewis to Chas. W. Goldsborough, Secretary of the Navy, which formed the basis for one of the accusations in the later Naval Enquiry on James Barron.
  The remainder of the material is from the years that Barron spent in exile in Copenhagen. Having arrived there in command of a commercial ship, Portia, in 1812, he was forced to sell the ship and remain in Denmark. His correspondence in connection with his attempts to make a living by his inventions show that he received patents on machines for spinning hemp into rope, cutting cork, kneading dough, and an improvised wind mill. His letter to Wm. Jones, Secretary of the Navy, asking an opportunity to serve his country at the conclusion of his sentence, 22 July 1813, remained unanswered. His correspondence of 1814 when he sold his European patents in expectation of an opportunity to return to the U.S. ended in disappointment. Much correspondence with his daughter, Jane A. Barron is from this period.
  - Records - of [U.S. Force] near Norfolk, 22 June 1810., 1 page. AD. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Letter - John Peake, Surry Place, to Lord Gambier. AD. ".. to prepare his Lordship for receiving a recommendation for an entirely new system for Vessels... ." 10 sheets. ALS. (A copy, taken 10 April 1812) 4 June 1811., pages. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - John Peake, Surry Place, to "My Lord" [Gambier], 30 June 1811., 20 pages. Incomplete. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    A long discussion of "Naval imbecility" etc.
  - Letter - W. Lewis to Chas. W. Goldsborough, Washington, 7 September 1811., 2 pages. ACop. (Box-folder 2:4)
    The report of the remarks made by Capt. James Barron to Mr. Lyons, British Consul, re: The Chesapeake-Leopard Affair. "I am now convinced that he is not only a coward, but a traitor...."
  - Letters - James Barron, Copenhagen, to Armistead & Kelly, Norfolk, Virginia, May 1812-April 1813., 5 letters. ACopsS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Re: Business matters.
  - Letters - James Barron, Copenhagen, to James & John Dunlop, London, May 1812-May 1813., 9 letters. ACopsS. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Concerned with the sale of the ship formerly commanded by Barron and other business matters.
  - Letters - James & John Dunlop, London, to Capt. James Barron, Copenhagen, August 1812-January 1813., 6 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 2:7)
    Re: the sale of the ship Portia, formerly commanded by Barron and other business matters.
  - Report - on the test of a cable made at the Chain Cable Manufactory of Capt. Samuel Brown, by J[?] P[?], 14 August 1812., 1 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Letter - Alex Barclay & Co., Gottenburg, to Capn. James Barron, Copenhagen, 22 August 1812., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
    Re: a previous letter.
  - Bill - of J.C. Stackneacht, Copenhagen, for tailoring to [James Barron], 23 August 1812., ADS. (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Letter - R. Fishey, Gothenburg, to James Barron, Copenhagen, 25 August 1812., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:11)
    Re: battles, "Lord Wellington's victory over the Marmont."
  - Letter - Tho[ma]s Witherspoon, Wilmington, to Allen McLand, 1 September 1812., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:12)
    Re: a suit against Capt. A. Murray in the District Court, District of Delaware.
  - Letter - Augustus Fleming, L[?], to Capt. James Barron, Copenhagen, 16 October 1812., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:13)
    Re: "Declaration of War on our part of 14th inst." And Capt. Hull's successful encounter with the Guerrier.
  - Letter - Alan Barclay & Co., Gothenburg, to Captn. James Barron, Copenhagen, 6 November 1812., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:14)
    Re: the purchase of Barron's ship.
  - Accounts - of Capt. [James] Barron, January-February 1813., 2 items. AD. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Letters - R. J. Cleveland, Kiel and Flemsburg, to James Barron, Copenhagen, April 1813., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 2:16)
    Re: business affairs connected with the hemp spinning machine.
  - Papers - defending the action of General Robert B. Taylor's actions in the defense of Craney Island, off Norfolk, April-December 1813., 12 items. ADr. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Letter - W. Gatewood, Nyberg, to Capt. James Barron, Copenhagen, 20 May 1813., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:18)
    Re: his activity on a ship of Capt. Bradley and his desire to return to Barron.
  - Petition - David Meade Randolph, London, to The Congress of the United States, 4 July 1813., 4 pages. ACops. (Box-folder 2:19)
    A petition to have his naval recommendation put into practice.
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to William Jones, Secretary of the Navy of the U.S. of America, Washington, 22 July 1813., 4 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 2:20)
    A defense of his action [in The Chesapeake-Leopard Affair] and an accusation against his accusers, especially Capt. Gordon.
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to William Jones, Secretary of the U.S. Navy, Washington, 22 July 1813., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 2:21)
    The term of his suspension having expired, Barron asks for opportunity to serve his country.
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to his daughter, Jane A. Barron, Hampton, Virginia, July-November 1813., 6 items. ALsS. (Box-folder 2:22)
    In one he mentions that he is writing to the Secretary of the Navy to offer his services to his country in the War.
  - Report - "Report of Board of Officers to General.", 1814., 5 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 2:23)
    Re: defense of Virginia, with mention of the Peninsula, Richmond, Petersburg, etc.
  - Bill - to John Gillespie from J.M. Forbes for a "rope laying machine.", 6 January 1814., AD. (Box-folder 2:24)
  - Letter - Belforn, Ellah, Rainals & Co., Elsinore, to James Barron, Copenhagen, 21 February 1814., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:25)
    Re: patent for rope machine.
  - Letter - Sam[ue]l Angus, Gothenburg, to James Barron, Copenhagen, 2 May 1814., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:26)
    Offer to carry communications to America on his next trip.
  - An Act and Deed - signed by James Barron, Commodore in the Navy of the United States, 21 May 1814., 4 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 2:27)
    Agreement to sell to John Murray Forbes the patent to a hemp spinning machine, patented in Denmark, Sweden, and Russia.
  - Letters - patent signed by Frederik VI, King of Denmark and Norway, for a dough kneading machine, to Nicolai Marshand, 24 May 1814., 4 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 2:28)
    Sale of the rights to the machine outside Denmark to James Barron.
  - Power of Attorney - given by James Barron in Copenhagen to his wife, daughter Jane, and Bullen Cooke, of Washington, D.C., 30 June 1814., 2 pages. ADS with ACopS. (Box-folder 2:29)
  - An unsigned account of the controversy between Philadelphia and Delaware from August 1812 to June 1814, June 1814., 7 pages. ADr,E. (Box-folder 2:30)
    Addressed to "Commodore Murray, at the Collector of Delaware." re: duties on the cargo of the British ship Superior.
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to his daughter, Jane A. Barron, Hampton, Virginia, June-October 1814., 2 pages. ALsS. (Box-folder 2:31)
    Re: Barron's attempts to return home and sale of his European patents.
  - Letters - J.M. Forbes, Copenhagen, to James Barron, Copenhagen and Gothenburg, June-November 1814., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 2:32)
    Written when Barron expected to get passage back to the U.S. from Gothenberg when he sold his European patents to Forbes.
  - Letter - S. Vyer, St. Petersburg, to Capt. James Barron, Copenhagen, 1 October 1814., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:33)
    Personal affairs.
  - Letter - J.W. Forbes, Copenhagen, 4 October 1814., 1 page. DS. (Box-folder 2:34)
    Grants permission to Capt. James Barron for the construction of a wind mill on which he, Forbes, holds patent rights.
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to Henry Wilson, American Consul, Nantes, France, 24 November 1814., 1 page. ACopS. (Box-folder 2:35)
    Re: chance for employment in France.
  - Letter - H.N. Fettyplace, Hamburg, to Capt. James Barron, Copenhagen, 3 January 1815., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:36)
    Preliminaries of peace were signed at Ghent between the British and American ministers.
  - Act - authorizing a Regular Force for the Defense of the Commonwealth. [Passed January the 18th, 1815.] [Richmond: Richie & Trueheart, 1815.], 18 January 1815., 4 pages. PD. (Box-folder 2:37)
  - Memorandum - regarding the formation of a Regiment of Artillery. Dated in Norfolk, but unsigned, 6 February 1815., 3 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 2:38)
  - Military recommendations - [Genl. Robert B. Taylor], military recommendations. Dated Norfolk, but unsigned, 14 February 1815., 3 pages. ACop. (Box-folder 2:39)
    "Taylor... is my brother."
  - Letters - Edward Armistead, Dartmoor Prison, England, and Copenhagen, to Capt. James Barron, Copenhagen, February-May 1815., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 2:40)
    Appeals to Barron to aid him, and a letter after his release from prison.
  - Letters - James Barron, London and Hamburg, to his daughter, Jane A. Barron, and wife, Mrs. Elizabeth M. Barron, Hampton, Virginia, March-August 1815., 4 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 2:41)
    News of his attempts to set up in business in Europe and of his new invention, a cork-cutting machine.
  - Letters - Peter H. Ferrau, Copenhagen, to James Barron, London and Hamburg, March-August 1815., 12 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 2:42)
    Business letters in which Ferrau expresses the sympathy in Copenhagen with the cause of Napoleon, and disappointed at his defeat.
  - Letter - J.M. Forbes, Copenhagen, to James Barron, Hamburg, 25 April 1815., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:43)
    Business affairs.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron], Hamburg, to P[eter] H. Ferrau, 2 June 1815., 1 page. 3 items. ACopS. (Box-folder 2:44)
    Re: transactions in tobacco. Enclosed: 2 receipts.
  - Letter - Sam[ue]l Myers, Norfolk, [Virginia], to James Barron, Copenhagen, 10 July 1815., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:45)
    Re: Barron's right of reinstatement among his countrymen.
  - Petition - of James Barron to the U.S. Secretary of State, 12 August 1815., 2 pages. ACopS. (Box-folder 2:46)
    For a patent on a machine for cutting corks.
  Series 3: Box 3
- Box 3, 1816-1820. (Box-folder 3:1-56)
  The correspondence of 1816 through 1820 begins with business and family letters received in Copenhagen. After his return to the U.S. in 1819 there is correspondence with the Navy Department and President Monroe regarding the reinstatement of Barron in a naval command. The correspondence of June 1819 to March 1820 with Capt. Stephen Decatur is preserved, along with an account of the duel in which Barron was gravely injured and Decatur killed. (See "The History of a transaction which there ought never to have been occasion for," an account of the duel written by James Barron in the Samuel Barron Papers, Box 1, Folder 8.) The correspondence with Capt. J. D. Elliott, his second, and reports of the controversies which followed the duel are included. Family letters include many from his daughter, Mrs. Jane Barron Hope.
  - Letter - Peter H. Ferrau, St. Croix, to James Barron, Copenhagen, February-September 1816., 3 letters. AlsS. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Re: his life in the West Indies where he has gone from Copenhagen.
  - Letter - Lorentz Aurst, Hamburg, to Commodore James Barron, Copenhagen, 5 April 1816., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:2)
    Business affairs; permission granted to import refined sugar into Russia.
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to Thomas Wilson, London, June 1816., 1 page. ACopS. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - James Barron, Copenhagen, to his daughter Jane A. Barron, Hampton, Virginia, June-July 1816., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Re: his hope of returning to U.S. within the year; and of the impending marriage of Jane.
  - Letter - [M. Myers], Bremen, to [James Barron], 10 October 1816., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
    News from home: re: Capt. Johnson and lucrative business in the Dismal Swamp Canal; trade with St. Iago De Cuba; Capt. Sinclair; plans to move the Naval Yard from Gosport to York, still undecided; Capt. Fawn's misfortune; flourishing condition of Norfolk; $100,000 subscribed to open the "Roan Oak Canal"; Chs. K. Mallory, Collector; Barron's family living in town after their country house burned.
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to his daughter, Jane A. Hope, Hampton, Virginia, November 1816., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)
    Re: his machine for cutting corks now successful, and his desire for a patent on it.
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to his daughter, Mrs. Jane A. Hope, Hampton, Virginia, 24 January 1817., 9 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:7)
    Re: her husband; detailed explanations of his cork cutting machine and his mill which "will grind 100 bushels of corn in 24 hours, can be completed for little more than a common pidgeon house."
  - John Rainals, Elsinore, to James Barron, Copenhagen, 18 February 1817., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:8)
    Re: a knife [for the cork cutting machine].
  - Contracts - Johannes Friis, James Barron, and P.T. Ferrau, March-November 1817., 2 items. ALS. (Box-folder 3:9)
    Contracts in Danish.
  - Contract - B. Kendar, Copenhagen, to Comm. James Barron, Copenhagen, 5 August 1817., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:10)
    Contract for Elliptical Valve Pump Boxes, to be made and sold by Barron after getting a Danish patent.
  - Authorization Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to Mrs. Jane A. Hope, Hampton, Virginia, 6 October 1817., 2 items. ALsS. (Box-folder 3:11)
    Authorization for the accountant of the U.S. Navy to pay the balance of his half-pay to Mrs. Elizabeth M. Barron or Mr. Wilton Hope (his son-in-law).
  - Letter - James Barron, Copenhagen, to John Myers, Baltimore, 12 October 1817., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:12)
    Introducing a Mr. Poulson.
  - Letter - G. L. Zachariae, Copenhagen, to James Barron, 12 November 1817., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:13)
    Re: commission given to Capt. Leech by Barron.
  - Document - James Barron and Johannis Friis, a document in Danish, 30 April 1818., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:14)
    Document in Danish.
  - Statement - James Barron, 1 June 1818., 1 page. ADS, E. (Box-folder 3:15)
    Statement re: his "new invented Pump" which he has offered to the Secretary of State.
  - Letter - C. Ferrau, Copenhagen, to James Barron, Elsinore, 24 June 1818., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:16)
    Wishing him a pleasant passage.
  - Will - of Richard Barron as made in 1787 and 1809, 25 June 1818., 4 pages. ACop. (Box-folder 3:17)
    Will Recorded at above date.
  - Letter - Carolina Colbiomsen, Copenhagen, to Capt. James Barron Elsinore, 28 June 1818., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:18)
    Re: St. Croix; and Barron's imminent departure.
  - Letter - A. Fibiger, Copenhagen, to Capt. James Barron, Elsinore and Hampton, Virginia, June-November 1818., 3 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 3:19)
    Written to Barron as he is waiting to sail and after his arrival in Virginia.
  - Document - for James Barron in Danish. 13 July 1818., PADS. (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Letter - James L. Ferrau, Edinburgh, to James Barron, Virginia Coffee House, London, 8 August 1818., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:21)
    James L. Ferrau having taken the degree of M.D. is returning to Copenhagen.
  - Letter - James Fraser, Liverpool, to Capt. [James] Barron, Talbot Inn, [London, England?], 27 August 1818., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:22)
    An offer for the purchase of the copyright of the cork cutting machine in Great Britain.
  - Letter - Charles K. Mallory, Washington, to Commodore James Barron, Hampton, 18 January 1819., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 3:23)
    "The President (James Monroe) takes a deep interest in your welfare... come on immediately to Washington and see the President himself.. .." Re: the debate in General Jackson's case.
  - Statement - John Quincy Adams, Washington, 22 February 1819., 2 pages. ACop. (Box-folder 3:24)
    Re: that Capt. James Barron applied for passage to the U.S. from Gothenberg to offer his services in the war; was refused passage because the ship was under a neutral cartel, in June 1814.
  - Statement - J.M. Forbes, 22 February 1819., 1 page. ACop. (Box-folder 3:25)
    Re: that he saw letter addressed by Capt. Barron to the U.S. Secretary of the Navy, in 1813 offering his services to the U.S. and that Barron sought passage to the U.S. in 1814.
  - Letter - James Barron, Washington, to James Monroe, President of the U. States, 8 March 1819., 6 pages. ADrS. (Box-folder 3:26)
    Request for readmission to the Navy, detailed denial of accusation which was contained in letter of Capt. William Lewis, 7 September 1811; he was in this country in September 1811 to April 1812.
  - Letter - Capt. Hugh G. Campbell, Charleston, to Capt. James Barron, Hampton, Virginia, 12 May 1819., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 3:27)
    A welcome home letter.